Frederick D. Patterson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Frederick D. Patterson Papers 1861-1988 1965-1988
MSS77597
Patterson, Frederick D. (Frederick Douglass), 1901-1988
15,000 items
41 containers
18.5 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
African American educational administrator and advocate. Correspondence, journal, writings and speeches, notes, reports, organizational records, clippings, printed materials, memorabilia, and miscellaneous items relating chiefly to Patterson's efforts, following his retirement as president of Tuskegee Institute in 1953, to preserve and develop African American institutions of higher learning.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carver, George Washington, 1864?-1943.; Clayton, Robert L.--Correspondence.; Colley, Nathaniel Sextus, 1918- --Correspondence.; Foster, Luther H. (Luther Hilton), 1913- --Correspondence.; Harriman, E. Roland (Edward Roland), 1895-1978--Correspondence.; Harris, Patricia, 1924-1985--Correspondence.; Jenkins, Matthew--Correspondence.; Mays, Benjamin E. (Benjamin Elijah), 1894-1984--Correspondence.; Moon, Henry Lee, 1901-1985--Correspondence.; Moton, Robert Russa, 1867-1940.; Patterson, Frederick D. (Frederick Douglass), 1901-1988.; Pierce, Ponchitta Anne, 1942- --Correspondence.; Player, Willa B.--Correspondence.; Price, Hollis F., 1904- --Correspondence.; Purves, Robert Ogden, 1895-1976--Correspondence.; Simon, Paul, 1928-2003--Correspondence.; Springer, Maida--Correspondence.; Weinberger, Caspar W.--Correspondence.; Williams, Franklin, 1917- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Phelps-Stokes Fund.; Robert R. Moton Memorial Institute.; Tuskegee Institute.; Tuskegee Institute. School of Veterinary Medicine.
Subjects
African American universities and colleges.; African Americans--Civil rights.; African Americans--Education.; Education--Africa.; Education--Nigeria.; Endowments--United States.; Federal aid to higher education.; Segregation--United States.
Places
Southern States.
Occupations
College administrators.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Frederick D. Patterson, African American educational administrator and advocate, were donated to the Library of Congress by Patterson's son, Frederick D. Patterson II, in 1988, 1989, and 1991.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division of the Library where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
The Patterson Papers form part of a sizable group of materials in the Manuscript Division relating to Black educators and the African American community. The Division's Booker T. Washington Papers, Moton Family Papers, and Frederick D. Patterson Papers constitute an important group of research materials relating to the first three presidents of Tuskegee Institute. The Moton Family Papers include correspondence between Patterson and Robert Russa Moton during the 1930s.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Frederick D. Patterson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1901, Oct. 10 Born, Washington, D.C.
1923 Doctor of veterinary medicine, Iowa State College, Ames, Iowa
1923 1927 Instructor, veterinary science, Virginia State College, Petersburg, Va.
1927 Master of science, Iowa State College, Ames, Iowa
1927 1928 Director of agriculture, Virginia State College, Petersburg, Va.
1928 1933 Head, Veterinary Division, Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Ala.
1932 Doctor of philosophy, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1933 1935 Director, School of Agriculture, Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Ala.
1935 Married Catherine E. Moton, daughter of Robert Russa Moton, second president of Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Ala.
1935 1953 President, Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Ala.
1943 1944 Established United Negro College Fund
1944 Published essay in What the Negro Wants, edited by Rayford W. Logan (Chapel Hill, N.C.: University of North Carolina Press. 352 pp.)
1953 1954 Inspected and evaluated educational resources in Nigeria on behalf of the World Bank/International Bank Commission
1953 1958 Director of Education, Phelps-Stokes Fund, New York, N.Y.
1956 Co-editor with William Hardin Hughes of Robert Russa Moton of Hampton and Tuskegee (Chapel Hill, N.C.: University of North Carolina Press. 238 pp.)
1958 1970 President, Phelps-Stokes Fund
1964 1966 President, United Negro College Fund, New York, N.Y.
1969 1973 President, Robert Russa Moton Memorial Institute, New York, N.Y.
1973 1984 Director, College Endowment Funding Plan, New York, N.Y.
1976 Published College Endowment Funding Plan (Washington, D.C.: American Council on Education. 120 pp.)
1985 Received White House Private Sector Initiative Commendation
1987 Awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom
1988, Apr. 26 Died, New Rochelle, N.Y.
1991 Posthumous publication of Patterson's autobiography, Chronicles of Faith, edited by Martia Graham Goodson (Tuscaloosa, Ala.: University of Alabama Press. 220 pp.)
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Frederick Douglass Patterson (1901-1988) span the years 1861-1988, with the largest group of materials dating from the period after 1965. The collection is composed of the personal papers of Patterson, third president of Tuskegee Institute and founder of the United Negro College Fund. They largely reflect his career following his retirement from Tuskegee in 1953 and highlight his efforts to preserve and develop historically Black institutions of higher learning. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, reports, organizational records, printed materials, writings and speeches, notes, clippings, memorabilia, and other miscellaneous items.
The Correspondence series of the Patterson Papers contains separate groupings of personal and general correspondence. Included in the personal correspondence are felicitations regarding Patterson's election to the presidency of Tuskegee Institute in 1935, his White House Private Sector Initiative Commendation in 1982, and his receipt of the Presidential Medal of Freedom from President Ronald Reagan in 1987. A few family letters from the early 1930s are also contained in this portion of the file. Items in the general correspondence include communications with organizations and individuals concerned with education, educational administration, business, fund-raising, and government.
The greatest concentration of materials in the Patterson Papers is found in the Subject File. The papers in this series cluster chiefly around Patterson's association with the Robert Russa Moton Memorial Institute and the College Endowment Funding Plan. Established by Patterson in the late 1950s in memory of his father-in-law and second president of Tuskegee Institute, the Robert Russa Moton Memorial Institute provided financial planning and training for historically Black colleges. Operating under the auspices of the institute was the College Endowment Funding Plan, devised by Patterson to endow small, poorly financed Black colleges, thereby securing their long-term stability. The file pertaining to the College Endowment Funding Plan traces the development of this program throughout the 1970s and 1980s, focusing on the passage of legislation that established federal matching grants for Black colleges. The materials document Patterson's work with educational administrators, financial officers, and government officials. Prominent correspondents include Caspar W. Weinberger, Willa B. Player of the United States Office of Education, and Congressman, later Senator, Paul Simon.
Other papers in the Subject File relate to the latter years of Patterson's tenure as president of the Phelps-Stokes Fund, a foundation devoted to improving housing and educational opportunities for African Americans and other disadvantaged people. Franklin H. Williams, Patterson's successor, is a prominent correspondent in the papers relating to the fund. A key file pertains to education in Africa, including a handwritten journal of Patterson's travels through Nigeria in 1953-1954 inspecting educational resources on behalf of the International Bank Commission. Materials relating to Tuskegee Institute in the Subject File reflect Patterson's continued interest in the school and include extensive correspondence with his successor as president, Luther H. Foster. Also present are brief items relating to aviation and low-cost housing at Tuskegee, as well as a sizable file concerning the institute's veterinary medicine school. Patterson's interest in Robert Russa Moton and botanist George Washington Carver is also exhibited in the Subject File. A typescript draft of a biography of Moton is among various biographical materials found in the file. Patterson served as executor of Carver's estate and participated in various memorials recognizing his achievements. The file contains copies of Patterson's speeches honoring Carver. Also included are transcripts of oral history interviews with Patterson conducted in 1980 and 1981 for the Phelps-Stokes Fund and the United Negro College Fund.
The Clippings File consists of newspaper clippings and magazine articles from the late 1930s through the 1970s, which Patterson annotated and organized according to a detailed classification system. Topics treated include civil rights, desegregation, regional education, the South, higher education, philanthropy, and other related issues. Also included are a significant group of draft and printed copies of Patterson's writings and speeches, as well as notes relating to various topics. Other writings and speeches not included in this classification scheme are located in the Miscellany series.
The Miscellany series holds, among other materials, a collection of personal clippings relating to Patterson's career and his work with the College Endowment Funding Plan. Included also are draft and print copies of speeches and writings by Patterson, as well as a small group of his published articles among the printed matter. Other materials include certificates, biographical data, telegrams, and memorabilia.
Prominent or frequent correspondents include Robert L. Clayton, Nathaniel Sextus Colley, E. Roland Harriman, Patricia Harris, Matthew Jenkins, Maida Springer Kemp, Benjamin E. Mays, Henry Lee Moon, Ponchitta Anne Pierce, Hollis F. Price, and Robert Ogden Purves.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1931-1988
Subject File, 1909-1988
Clippings File, 1939-1981
Miscellany, 1861-1988
Container List
- Correspondence, 1931-1988 (Box 1-5)
  Personal and general correspondence, with attached and related matter, organized into separate groupings and alphabetically therein by name of person or organization or by type of material.
  Chronologically arranged within folders.
  - Personal (Box 1)
    - Congratulatory
      - 1935, (3 folders)
      - 1973-1988, (5 folders)
    - Family, 1931-1935
  - General
    - "A-B" miscellaneous, 1969-1988, (4 folders)
    - Clayton, Robert L., 1977-1985 See also Container 16, Moton, Robert Russa, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Colley, Nathaniel Sextus, 1970-1987
    - Cowley, W. H., 1970-1978
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1971-1988, (3 folders)
    - Davis, Lincoln J., 1972-1977, undated
    - Dawson, William L., 1981-1985
    - Dillon, Wilton S., 1974-1983
    - "D-F" miscellaneous, 1971-1988, (4 folders)
    - Gandy, Stewart B., 1976-1978
    - Garcia, Jose, 1972-1974
    - Gibson, Jessie, 1972-1974
    - Glick, G. Wayne, 1978-1987, undated
    - Gossett, William T., 1971-1985
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1972-1988
    - Harriman, E. Roland, 1972-1988 (Box 3)
    - Harris, Patricia, 1978
    - Hastings, Lawrence B., Sr., 1973-1975
    - Hogan, Lawrence, 1975-1984
    - Howard, Oscar C., 1973-1984
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1971-1988, (2 folders)
    - Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa, 1980-1984
    - "I" miscellaneous, 1977-1980
    - Jenkins, Matthew, 1979-1988
    - "J" miscellaneous, 1971-1987
    - Kemp, Maida Springer, 1973-1974
    - "K-L" miscellaneous, 1970-1985, (2 folders)
    - Martz & Lundy, Inc., 1976-1980
    - Mays, Benjamin E., 1974-1984
    - Melady, Thomas R., 1983-1987
    - Miner, Ernest, 1984-1986
    - Moon, Henry Lee, 1973-1985
    - Moton, Laura, 1977
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1956-1988, (3 folders)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1973-1980 (Box 4)
    - "N-O" miscellaneous, 1971-1988, (5 folders)
    - Perspectives International, 1979-1981, undated
    - Pierce, Ponchitta Anne, 1973
    - Player, Willa B., 1975-1988
    - Pray, Frances, 1969-1982
    - Price, Hollis F., 1975-1982
    - Purves, Robert Ogden, 1973-1976
    - "P" miscellaneous, 1971-1986, (3 folders)
    - Richardson, Harry V., 1972-1984
    - Rivinus, David, 1970-1973
    - Rowe, William, 1982-1987
    - "R" miscellaneous, 1972-1987
    - Stillman College, Tuscaloosa, Ala., 1981-1987
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1955-1987, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Texas Association of Developing Colleges, 1974-1977
    - "T-V" miscellaneous, 1970-1987, (4 folders)
    - Walker, Grace, 1969-1975
    - "W-Z" miscellaneous, 1955-1988, (4 folders)
    - Unidentified, 1955-1982, undated
- Subject File, 1909-1988 (Box 6-32)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, circular letters, minutes, financial records, printed materials, occasional writings and speeches, notes, and miscellaneous items.
  Organized alphabetically by topic or name of organization and within these headings by subject or type of material. Chronologically arranged within folders.
  - Academy for Educational Development, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Africa See also Containers 17-21, Phelps-Stokes Fund
    - Africare, 1973-1984
    - General correspondence, 1957-1978
    - Manuscript notes, 1959
    - Miscellaneous documents, 1961, undated
    - Nigeria
      - Handwritten journal, 1953-1954
      - Preliminary Report on Education in Nigeria, by Patterson, 1953-1954
      - Printed materials, 1961-1970
    - Report on visit to ten African countries by E. B. Evans and Patterson, 1969
    - United Nations Economic Commission for Africa, 1970 (Box 7)
      - Proceedings
      - Reports
  - American Council on Education
    - Annual meeting, 1976
    - Correspondence, 1974-1978, 1983-1984, (6 folders)
    - Miscellaneous items, 1972-1978, undated (Box 8)
    - Office of Leadership Development in Higher Education, 1973-1978, (3 folders)
    - Printed materials, 1973-1978, (2 folders)
  - Architects
    - Correspondence, 1968-1979
    - Drawings, 1972
  - Benjamin E. Mays National Educational Resource Center, Washington, D.C., 1983-1984 (Box 9)
  - Bennett College, Greensboro, N.C.
    - Board of trustees, minutes and reports, 1963-1977
    - Correspondence, 1960-1982
    - Investment and finance committees, minutes and reports, 1973-1981
    - Miscellaneous items, 1956-1974, undated
  - Black higher education, reports
    - "The Case for Private Black Colleges," by Kenneth S. Tollett, [ 1982? ]
    - "Public Policy and Private Black Higher Education," [ 1985 ]
  - Black Retail Action Group, 1985-1986
  - Booker T. Washington Foundation, board of trustees (Box 10)
    - Annual meeting, 1973
    - Bylaws and personnel manual, 1977-1980
    - Contract résumés, 1975-1979, (2 folders)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1984, (4 folders)
    - Financial documents, 1974-1978
    - Memoranda, 1969-1981 (Box 11)
    - Minutes, 1970-1982, (2 folders)
    - Miscellaneous reports, 1975-1981, undated
  - Cablecommunications Resource Center, 1974
  - Carver, George Washington
    - Biography, correspondence and contract, 1939-1944
    - George Washington Carver Foundation, 1940-1974
    - Memorials to Carver, correspondence, 1970-1979, (2 folders)
    - Printed materials, 1970-1977, undated (Box 12)
    - Speeches and notes by Patterson, 1946-1977, undated
  - Charles Stewart Mott Foundation, Black College Advisory Committee, minutes and reports, 1980-1984, (3 folders)
  - College Endowment Funding Plan
    - Challenge Grant Amendment of 1983, 1977-1986
    - Correspondence
      - 1971-1976, (2 folders)
      - 1977-1987, undated, (9 folders) (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978
    - Statements and writings, 1972-1983, undated
    - White House Initiative, Private Sector Partnership, 1982
  - Council on Foreign Relations
    - Circular letters, 1970-1979
    - Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Box 14)
    - Printed materials, 1972-1980, undated
  - Flemmie P. Kittrell Endowment Fund
    - Correspondence, 1958-1976
    - Printed materials, 1946-1968
  - Ford Foundation, 1965-1979, (4 folders)
  - Foundation Center, 1969-1974
  - Health, Education, and Welfare, Department of
    - Office of Education
      - Advisory Council on Developing Institutions, annual report, 1977
      - Correspondence, 1970-1973
      - Developing Institutions Study Group, 1977, (3 folders)
      - National Advisory Committee on Black Higher Education and Black Colleges and Universities, 1977-1982, (5 folders) (Box 15)
  - Interdenominational Theological Center
    - Correspondence, 1970-1984
    - Reports, memoranda, etc., 1961, 1971-1975, (2 folders)
  - Management consultants, 1969-1978, undated (Box 16)
  - Moton, Robert Russa, biography of See also Container 2, Clayton, Robert L.
    - Correspondence, 1963-1977
    - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1917-1986, undated
    - Typescript draft and notes, undated
  - National Association for Equal Opportunity in Higher Education
    - Correspondence, 1975-1986
    - Printed materials, 1977-1988
    - Reports and statements, 1970-1975
  - National Business League
    - Board of directors, minutes, 1960, 1970-1980
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1957-1981, (3 folders)
  - National Business League (Box 17)
    - Printed materials, 1960-1981, undated, (2 folders)
    - Reports, 1960-1978, undated
  - National Medical Fellowships, Inc., 1974
  - New School for Social Research, 1963
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund See also Containers 6-7, Africa
    - African Student Aid Fund
      - Benefactors, correspondence with
        - Charles Merrill Trust, 1967-1972, undated
        - Edgar J. Kaufman Charitable Trust, 1969-1972
        - Mary Harriman Trust, 1967-1971
      - Board of directors, minutes, 1970-1980, (3 folders)
      - Bylaws and certificate of incorporation, 1966
      - Correspondence, 1970-1988
      - History, 1975
      - Miscellaneous items, 1970-1974, undated
    - Board of trustees (Box 18)
      - Bylaws, 1931-1976
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1953-1988, (5 folders)
      - Finance Committee, 1955, 1982
      - Membership, 1957-1987, undated
      - Minutes
        - 1953-1976, (2 folders)
        - 1978-1987, (3 folders) (Box 19)
      - Newsletters, 1954-1956
      - President's reports, 1955-1979
    - Cooperative College Development Program
      - Conference schedules, 1965-1968
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1965-1975, undated
      - Directory of institutions, [ 1968? ]
      - History, 1964-1968
      - Matching grant requests, 1965-1970
      - Miscellaneous items, 1964-1972, undated (Box 20)
      - Progress report, 1967-1974
      - Writings, notes, and speeches, 1966-1969, undated
    - History by Ponchitta Anne Pierce, [ 1973 ], (4 folders)
    - Negro handbook, 1960-1962, undated
    - Negro reference book, 1967-1969, undated
    - Oral history interview with Patterson, 1981
    - Ralph J. Bunche Memorial Project, 1976-1978, undated
    - Reports and writings
      - "Booker Washington Institute" [Liberia], by Patterson, 1959
      - Miscellaneous
        - 1947-1976
        - 1979-1980, undated (Box 21)
      - "Self-Study of the Phelps-Stokes Fund," 1979
  - Professional Institute of American Management Associations, 1975-1978
  - Robert Russa Moton Memorial Institute
    - African students, 1966-1975
    - Bylaws and personnel manual, 1972
    - Financial documents
      - Auditor's report, 1978
      - Income and expenses reports, 1969-1973
      - Miscellaneous items, 1962-1988, undated
      - Treasurer's reports, 1969-1973
    - History, 1957-1962, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1980
    - Moton College Service Bureau
      - Correspondence, 1967-1971
      - Reports, 1971, undated
    - Moton colleges and universities (institutions participating in Moton Institute development programs), correspondence and grant request forms (Box 22)
      - Clark College, Atlanta, Ga., 1970-1985
      - Dillard University, New Orleans, La., 1970-1984
      - Fiske University, Nashville, Tenn., 1971-1977
      - Florida A & M University, Tallahassee, Fla., 1970-1983
      - Hampton University, Hampton, Va., 1970-1985
      - Huston-Tillotson University, Austin, Tex., 1970-1984
      - Jackson State College, Jackson, Miss., 1969-1984
      - Kentucky State College, Frankfort, Ky., 1970-1972
      - Morehouse College, Atlanta, Ga., 1967-1988
      - Morris Brown College, Atlanta, Ga., 1970-1986
      - North Carolina A & T State University, Greensboro, N.C., 1970-1978
      - North Carolina Central University, Durham, N.C., 1970-1981, undated
      - Paine College, Augusta, Ga., 1970-1980
      - Rust College, Holly Springs, Miss., 1971-1986
      - Saint Augustine's College, Raleigh, N.C., 1956-1982
      - Tuskegee University, Tuskegee, Ala., 1970-1986, 1956-1982
      - Virginia Union University, Richmond, Va., 1957-1979
      - Xavier University, New Orleans, La., 1970-1987
      - Miscellaneous
        - A-L, 1969-1987
        - M-W, 1957-1983 (Box 23)
    - Moton Conference Center, Capahosic, Va.
      - Library, 1968-1971, undated
      - Management, 1959-1975, undated
      - Physical facilities
        - Architectural drawings, 1966-1971, undated
        - Contracts and proposals, 1964-1973, undated
        - Correspondence, 1965-1976
        - Miscellaneous, 1965, undated
    - Moton Development Consortium
      - Correspondence, 1971-1976
      - Reports and notes, 1971, undated
    - Printed materials, 1982-1985, undated
    - Projects and proposals, 1958-1971
    - Reports (Box 24)
      - "Black Colleges and Federal Support of Higher Education," [ 1971? ]
      - "Title III of the Higher Education Act of 1965 Up-dated," by Willa B. Player, 1983
        - Study, "Growing Federal Role in Support of Higher Education," notes and clippings, [ 1972 ]
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1965-1966
  - Sloan Foundation, 1969-1971
  - Southern Education Foundation
    - Board of directors, minutes, 1965-1983, (2 folders)
    - Correspondence and memoranda
      - 1965-1968, (3 folders)
      - 1969-1983, (5 folders) (Box 25)
    - Financial documents, 1965-1969, 1975, (3 folders)
    - Internship program, 1972
    - Miscellaneous items, 1969-1972, undated (Box 26)
    - Printed materials, 1976-1987
    - Reports
      - "Federal Funds and Black Colleges," by Virginia Frank, 1972
      - "Some Information on Supply and Demand Related to Child Care and Development in the South," [ 1971 ]
  - Technical Assistance Consortium to Improve College Services, 1976-1981
  - Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Ala.
    - Army Air Corps, 1943, 1983
    - Aviation at Tuskegee Institute, 1968, 1979
    - Board of trustees
      - Memoranda, 1967-1987, (3 folders)
      - Minutes (Box 27)
        - 1965-1977, (7 folders)
        - 1978-1986, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Centennial campaign, 1977
    - Correspondence
      - 1931-1966, (4 folders)
      - 1967-1988, (10 folders) (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous items, 1909-1987
    - President's reports, 1969-1985 (Box 30)
    - Printed material